<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for Christopher Syms gent. and his way and method of teaching the effect thereof, and his end therein, against many foule and false aspersions. VVherein and whereby is averred and maintained that all persons, who can see, heare and speake, may bee easily taught to read. And that all children, which can read may be easily taught to understand the Latine speech.</title>
            <author>Syms, Christofer.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113866</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14228</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14228)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1467:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for Christopher Syms gent. and his way and method of teaching the effect thereof, and his end therein, against many foule and false aspersions. VVherein and whereby is averred and maintained that all persons, who can see, heare and speake, may bee easily taught to read. And that all children, which can read may be easily taught to understand the Latine speech.</title>
                  <author>Syms, Christofer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Society of Stationers],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in Anno 1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reading --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reading, Psychology of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Latin language --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14228:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14228:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN</hi> APOLOGY FOR <hi>CHRISTOPHER SYMS</hi> Gent. and his way and Method of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, the effect thereof, and his end therein, againſt many foule and falſe Aſperſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherein and whereby is averred and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that all perſons, who can ſee, heare and speake, may bee eaſily taught to read.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that all Children, which can read, may be eaſily taught to underſtand the Latine Speech.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Vide, Fide.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in Anno 1633.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14228:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14228:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Apology, for <hi>Chriſtopher Syms</hi> Gent. and his way and method of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, the effects thereof, and his <hi>end therein, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Cinditur incertum ſtudia in contraria vulgus:</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>So it was in the Poets time, ſo is now, and ſo it will be, when I am gone, and ſleepe with my Fathers. Yet while I am broad waking in this lyncean eye ſighted age, wherein every man is apt to bee peeping and ſpying, above, beneath, and round about ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſpecially a ſtranger, (ſuch perſons for the moſt, part being the buſieſt, who have the narroweſt eyes both in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion and judgement) the peircing glaunces of ſome ſhallow, raſh, preiudicate, uncertaine and ſlanderous cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, darted at me, and my practiſe in teaching, either from ignorant, or malevolent aſpects, or both, enforce from me a reflection, and conſtraine me to ſay ſomewhat more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely for both againſt them: wherein if I ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to avoide the various paſſions, and ungrounded cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſuch perſons, who are not endued with ability to iudge of the diſpoſitions of mindes, or the qualities and ends of workes and actions; I might as juſtly draw on my ſelfe the cenſure of weakenes, folly, and madnes, as mine honeſt artificiall endeavours have undeſervedly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly pulled upon me the imputation of impoſtor, cheator conjurer, and crochetter to get money; and that I would get ſome money in my purſe and be gone; that when my ſlender skill had ſhewed ſome reall effect, it would not hold, that the children whom I have taught, can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but whilſt I am preſent, and ſuch other fantaſticall cenſures, I know not what. Theſe giddy indiſcreet cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14228:3"/>
doubtles have proceeded from perſons ignorant of any cauſe; who like young &amp; ill ſented hounds not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their game run on in the chace, and ſpend their mouths for company. Let them barke<hi>: Quibuſdam canibus ſic inna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum eſt latrare, ut non pro feritate, ſed pro conſuetudine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trent:</hi> as their good words cannot much benefit, ſo their evill words will doe little hurt. For, <hi>Quicquid faciunt, ex morbo faciunt, non ex judicio,</hi> they extoll and praiſe (for the moſt part) the unworthy, and cry downe and condemne the deſerving and innocent; <hi>faciunt quod ſolent, non quod mereor, male de me loquuntur homines, ſed mali &amp; maniaci;</hi> they will be medling. But my drift and ſcope is, not to give ſatifaction to ſuch: it were a vaine, endles, and would be a fruitleſſe labour. <hi>Rumor vulgi attonitus;</hi> I leave them to their owne folly and madnes, and I am content to paſſe by, and ſlyde away as a ſtrange dog doth thorow a towne or ſtreete, when every domeſtick curre hath a ſnap at him. Such like is humane curteſie<hi>:</hi> and more envious, inhumane, and barbarous are the Engliſh to their owne countrymen, then other nations: I am not glad, that I can ſpeake it. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer autem ſi Marcus Cato, ſi Laelius ſaepiens, ſi alter Cato, ſi duo Scipiones iſta loquerentur de me.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Laelij,</hi> thoſe <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pioes,</hi> thoſe <hi>Curij,</hi> thoſe <hi>Catoes,</hi> who attribute nothing to the vulgar idoles, opinion and fame, envy and detraction, which for the moſt part carries all now; who never enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a preiudicate opinion, either of perſons, or of things; who never vent a raſh cenſure without mature delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon events and iſſues of workes, are the men whoſe good eſteeme and good report I affect and ſeeke, and that not for mine owne ſake meerely, but for the workes ſake cheifly, which I have in hand<hi>:</hi> the proofe whereof will maintaine it ſelfe, to be worth reſpect and embracement of a commonwealth; which ſhall with Gods helpe, if mine induſtry be accepted, benfit the world, when I am gone, if the envious, <hi>quaſi canis in praeſepi,</hi> hinder not: to prevent whoſe malice and oppoſition, it is very neceſſary by this way of Apology, to ſtop the wide mouthes of ignorant
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14228:3"/>
and envious detractors, beſides whom none will diſallow the fitnes, and in ſome caſes the neceſſity of apologies and defences; as in this ſubject of this mine apology, whereby I doubt not, but in ſome meaſure to make it evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that my method and experiment of teaching is of greater and better conſequence, then to be ſlighted, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or rejected: And I hope no teacher, no ſcholler, no man diſparaged thereby, although it proceede from a meane and obſcure author, who never ſought employment by a <hi>ſi quis,</hi> nor glory out of other mens diſgraces. If the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod were a tricke or toy, that could not be conveyed to others, but muſt vaniſh with my ſelfe, I would eaſily yeeld, it were of no value: but it is otherwiſe, it may be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all poſterity. It is aſwell the inſtruction of children in the Latine language, as alſo in reading the Engliſh with more alacrity, celerity, and facility, then formerly; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample whereof may be followed in other languages. I am verily perſwaded that few teachers have hitherto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe delighted in that function, then as carriers, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, bargemen, and the like doe in their painfull, hard, ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and perillous journeyes and voyages, which they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe meerely for the ſuſtentation of life. For mine owne part, ſince I found the validity of the method, I never tooke delight in any earthly thing, but in teaching, and ſhould delight much more, if I might be recompenced. As for profit, I ſuppoſe, that every man, who knoweth nothing of my education, inclination, or meane qualification, can and will ſay for me, that other more advantageous courſes of life might have beene undertaken, if advancement or gaine had beene the object of mine undertaking<hi>:</hi> And thoſe, who doe truely know me (I doubt not) will ſoone deliver their opinion, it being required, that I am <hi>tam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae, quam caulae mediocritèr adaptatus,</hi> and that I make not the profeſſion my <hi>ultimum refugium</hi> as being neceſſitous, and fit for nothing elſe, nor yet for that. Although it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, but that many unexpert men doe ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controulment, in divers places, both in <hi>England</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14228:4"/>
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> whom the meaner ſort of people, and ſome who will not be ſo ranked, becauſe they accept ſlender and baſe hyre, employ and applaud, and let their children ſpin out time with them, untill they have gotten even as much ſkill as their teachers. Such a one could I point out in this citties ſuburbs, who underſtandeth not the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>e</hi> and <hi>ae</hi> dipthong; as I can make appeare under his owne hand writing. It is an ordinary practiſe in <hi>England,</hi> for men who have themſelves no faculty in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, (to the end they may raiſe unto themſelves a liuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,) to take into their houſes ſtipendary mercenaries, teachers of the Latine, and French, Muſitians, Dancers, &amp;c. And one among the reſt there is who hath thereby got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſingular fame ſpread far and neere, who leaving an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall (abuſively ſo called) trade, more gainefull, not ſo lawfull, hath by the encomiaſtick narration of friends, drawne into his tuition the ſonnes of many worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: with what proficiency they have come off, let them boaſt who found the ſucceſſe. Of the danger that attends birds, who run too earely from their neſts, as the Patridge and the Lapwing, I will ſay nothing. But little probability is there that any good foundation of the Latine can bee laide, when the inſtructers are often changed, as in ſuch a courſe without doubt they are: for every of them will ſtart for the better ſtipend, and oftentimes offences on the one ſide or the other cauſeth ſeparation. I my ſelfe knew one man in England, who ſet up the trade, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two yeares changed the maſter of his ſhop ſeven times, <hi>qui ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt, nuſquàm eſt; non venit vulnus ad cicatricem, ubi crebra medicamenta tentantur.</hi> But I digreſſe<hi>:</hi> Painefull is the profeſſion, if it be exerciſed with diligence, as it ought: and yet thereof doth ariſe little gaine, love, thankes or curteſie, from many unthankefull perſons, who, if their children make good progreſſe and attaine the end, attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute nothing to the teacher, but all to the childes ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to time, and the booke, falſly imagining, that there is no Art in teaching, but onely following, as they terme it.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14228:4"/>
And contrarywiſe if by reaſon of naturall defects, the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher cannot infuſe ſo much into their children, as into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more acute, or if their children by reaſon of naturall deficiency of eyes or tongues be not able, when they are earneſtly haſtened, to utter what they conceive, nor the parents endued with ſkill and patience to extract it from their children, then the teacher muſt be blamed and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and peradventure goe unrewarded, the parents ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſidering natures imperfections, and the imbecillity of ſuch capacityes, nor the tender care that a wiſe teacher ought to take of ſuch, leaſt he doe more hurt then good. Many ſuch have I here met with, who beſides non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, after a good effect of mine Art and induſtry upon wooden and leaden ſubjects both yong and old, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded me with obloquy, railing, and detraction, and ſome with violence: yea, where I did beſt and deſerved moſt, I reaped <hi>Billinſgate</hi> friendſhip and entertainment, and <hi>Pye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corner,</hi> and <hi>Picks-hatch</hi> farewell. In one place for forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings I got a Boxe, but no money to put in a boxe: in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the huſband invited me, and the wife gave me a fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebach</hi> for <hi>dough a doris,</hi> not a cup, but a paile of hotewater on my head, when I was ſhutting the doore at my departure. <hi>Si quiſquam huius procellae cauſam ulteriùs inveſtigare cupiat, ab archimagiro in culina ſciſcitetur: exin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de enim aqua calefacta: ſin minus, lararij or acula petas, quae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, niſi praecentor ejus, explicare poterit.</hi> To me it ſeemeth more a riddle, then this Latine ſentence can be to them, that know not the ſubject and members thereof, that a dignified Dame ſhould call me cheating knave, and that her Cavallier ſhould ſmite me, when I had given no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, nor had gotten any money for a yeare and halfes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; but was rather cheated of my Art and induſtry<hi>:</hi> and that with as much more loſſe of time, Art, and induſtry, her Goſſip ſhould ſcold at me, and ſcald me, no cauſe of quarrell being knowne or declared, albeit it were deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. When I conſider the parties, I admire not their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties kind charitable creatures, who would rather, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14228:5"/>
I ſhould periſh, then they pay me the due reward of my labours. Well yet there is a fourth thing, which might as much diſcourage me from the proſecution of my profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as the other three, great paines, ſmall gaines, and baſe requitall, that is, the ſlender &amp; mean eſtimation the world receiveth and holdeth of the profeſſors, when it ſpeaketh according to its weak judgment contemptuouſly, thus, he is but a Schoolemaſter a Pedagoge. If any be unworthy, mens unthankfulnes and want of judgment is the cauſe; for that they make not better choyce, nor will confer bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſalary upon thoſe, who are more worthy and more able. Surely they ought to be worthy: for upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it reſts, whether the ſons of the Nobles and Gentry get, and loue learning, for they have the ſeaſoning of them, and a work of weight it is, and muſt be done in their child-hood, or never: and without all doubt the common wealth is much endammaged, yea, and the Church ſuffereth, when the Nobles be <hi>agrammati,</hi> and on the contrary both flouriſh, when they be <hi>philomuſi,</hi> and <hi>philologi.</hi> By theſe precedent reaſons it may appeare to the judicious Reader, that I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it to be my greater glory to defend the work, then the workman. For what have I, who am but a clod of clay, which I have not received from the giver of every good and perfect gift? If then I have received a talent, I have together received a charge, that I ſhall not hide that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: and what is it being not communicated? of the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment whereof my conſcience informeth me, that a ſtrict account will be exacted at that dreadfull day, when every ſteward muſt give a reckoning of his ſtewardſhip. If there were no more in it but morality, I would not for vertues ſake be <hi>telluris inutile pondus.</hi> The love of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick likewiſe together with mine owne delight may and doth incite me: for other incouragement have I none, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I doe it; but becauſe <hi>non nobis nati ſumus;</hi> and to the end, that the practiſe thereof might win credit to the experiment for the contemplative demonſtration on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without the proofe of practiſe might worthily be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14228:5"/>
Peradventure ſome of that rabble, whom I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before, whoſe deriſions I contemn, and whoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections are not worth the anſwering, will ſay, what fellow is this? And what great thing is this, that needeth this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology? And why was not this way of teaching (if there be ſuch a thing) found out in former ages, as well as now? And were not children taught to read, and to underſtand the Latine ſpeech, before this fellow was? True; But many failed even in reading, and in the Latine, there were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes as many, or more deficients then proficients. Then I ſay, for the firſt part of the work, the device and practice being wholly and meerely invented by my ſelfe, is a way, whereby any perſon yong or old, acute or obtuſe may be taught to read with facility and delight, both to teacher and learner, to which little memory is requiſite, but a full pronuntiation is very neceſſary. By this method a child of perfect ſpeech may be made able to ſpell engliſh truly and readily whatſoever be propoſed, ſillable after ſillable, the memory being not charged with two at once within one quarter of a yeare; yea it may, it hath beene effected within a moneth, and in leſſe time. And doth it not then neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, that that childe, who can give every letter how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever tranſpoſed its true ſound muſt eaſily and ſpeedily read, and that long before he bee fit to learne the Latine tongue, beginning at five yeares of age? Will any ſenſible man deny it? It is a very plain and eaſie way and method, not far fetched, nor much ſtrained for, but therein a very little Art added to nature. For the ſecond, it is not meerely mine own, but partly M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Lilies:</hi> for hee gave me the hint thereof: Wherein if any man concurre with me in ſcience practick for the common good, I repine not, but rather rejoyce; becauſe the experiment may be more authentick by a twofold or triple cord. Howſoever <hi>cum capitis peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo,</hi> I will maintain it to be ſuch a way and method, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the moſt indocile and obtuſe child, whoſoever he bee, if <hi>animi compos,</hi> may within one quarter of a yeare after he can read well, be made expert and perfect in the variation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14228:6"/>
of the Verb, as of all other parts declinable; yea to give Engliſh for latine, and Latine for Engliſh readily and truly thorowout all Verbs whatſoever, the Verb and his ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication being given, and the child being ſupplyed with the preterperfect tenſe of the Indicative mood, untill he have learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Lilies</hi> Rules to find out the ſame: and ſo conſequently, foraſmuch as the difficulty and intricacy of the Latine conſiſteth in the infinitenes of the Verbs varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is above one thouſand in both voyces, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſignes of the Optative, Potentiall, and Subjunctive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared, it will make every child, who is <hi>animi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos,</hi> (as I ſaid before) docile and capable of underſtanding the Latine, and that within three or foure yeares, and ſometimes in much leſſe time: As for writing copiouſly, and ſpeaking fluently, who knoweth not, that much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding muſt furniſh with words and phraſe, and frequent ſpeaking bring facility and readines of ſpeech. Both which wayes and methods are ſuch, as when they ſhal be layd open, every literate man will ſay, why did not I ſee this, as well as he? and thoſe men, who now envy, deride and ſcoffe, and ſuch others, who plot, combine, and load me with detraction, and ſtir wormaniſh and worſe faction, will alter their opinions, and embrace my poore invention and experiment<hi>:</hi> which in due time I will tender to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend authority, teaching in the meane time, none but the lawfull Grammar.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of my ſtudy and exquiſition to find out a more familiar and eaſie way of teaching <hi>àprimordijs,</hi> then had formerly beene received, was the conſideration of the tedious time of ſeven, eight, nine, yea ten years, (may I ſay, no more) which was and is ſpent in teaching the Latine ſpeech, and foure, five, and ſix in the way of reading, with much auſterity and bitternes to the great diſcouragement of children, before it can be brought to perfection; nay yet after much toyle on the teachers part, and torture of the children, many aſwell the ſons of the Nobility and Gentry, as of meaner perſons faile, and never attain what
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14228:6"/>
they goe about, unleſſe ſome more acute then the reſt: and many ſo imperctly taught to read, that when they come to learn the Latine, both themſelves and their teachers tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough their unreadines in reading, unleſſe it be firſt recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, are much vexed; which produceth no ſmall obſtacle to their progreſſe. And ſo by that meanes many good wits beaten out of heart, and brought into hatred both of books and learning, yea and teacher too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; not few, when grown up to good ſtature thorough the ſharpenes of ſome tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers driven into deſperate courſes. I can truly ſay that of divers children brought to me, ſome whereof were eight yeares old, ſome nine, ſome ten, ſome eleven, ſome twelve, one fourteen, not all the Sons of common perſons, nor ſuch as had been neglected, but had been formerly taught with care and coſt, none could read ſo much as meanly well, which my way would have made them do by that time they had accompliſhed ſeven years of age, had they begun at five. And moreover ſome of them, and ſome yonger ſo affrighted and diſcouraged, that untill I had altered their temper with lenity and familiarity, they would quake and ſhake and ſweat, when they came to the buſineſſe. How ſome of their parents and friends have requited me, who craved not, nor expected my wages, till my work was done, I will not now complain; let me only ſay, that many withdrew their children from me ſurreptitiouſly to ſave their moneyes, and permitted me not to make appear what was done, leſt I ſhould have challenged what was due<hi>:</hi> And to diſgrace me yet further, when I had almoſt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the work for many of them, for the matter of reading; they ſet up a fly upon the wheele, that preſently cryed, what a duſt have I ſtirred? when as the horſe heels had ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the duſt, before the fly ſettled on the coach-whell. Let them go on with their giddines, avarice, and baſeneſſe, and let their own experience find, that <hi>planta, quae ſaepius tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur, non convaleſcit;</hi> that time will not be called again, that there is Art in teaching, which may and can ſharpen and quicken hebetude, and help imperfect ſpeech very
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14228:7"/>
much in infancy, before long cuſtome have confirmed it. What effect in the Latine my labours have produced anſwereable to the efficacie, which I attribute to my Method, if any man require an account, I appeale in the firſt place to the teſtimonie of <hi>Maſter William Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Captaine of his Majeſties Poſt Barke, and <hi>Maſter William Scot</hi> his Majeſties Seaacher of his Port of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> who within one moneth after I had undertaken a childe of <hi>Maſter Scots,</hi> who was my firſt Scholler but no acute one, (as the iſſue will manifeſt now he is off from my method) heard the ſame child being then halfe a year ſhort of nine yeares of age, give Latine for Engliſh, and Engliſh for Latine thoroughout a Verb choſen by one of them, and it was <hi>expergiſcor.</hi> Now becauſe it little availed to tell of ſuch beginnings, unleſſe it may appeare, that they were ſeconded with like proceedings, and becauſe he was taken from me above halfe a year ſince, at the earneſt ſuit of the mother, <hi>quaſi invito patre,</hi> when I had ſpent two years and a quarter upon him, or little more, and for that I am not aſſured, that that man, to whoſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hee was next committed, will either give mee or him our dues, and becauſe I am well aſſured that he will not proceede with the like profit being out of his firſt Method by reaſon of his hebetude and yong yeares being but eleven compleate, momorie and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being not confirmed, and becauſe much woma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh clamour hath beene throated out againſt mee touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, thoſe of the faction falſly ſurmizing him to bee my Maſter-Peece, and that if hee were taken off, I were utterly ſupplanted, <hi>&amp; quod ſalvus ſupereſt Artifex,</hi> It is therefore expedient, that I ſhew to what ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Childe was growne in our two yeares, which was ſuch, as he was able to read <hi>Tullyes Offices</hi> into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh at firſt ſight, and then neceſſarily able to tranſlate it, and when hee had tranſlated it, to read it againe into true Latine, having never committed any one clauſe of the booke to memory; he did often in the preſence of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14228:7"/>
divers perſons, the Booke being opened at adventure, read the Latine Teſtament into Engliſh; hee could likewiſe for ſhort ſentences, ſuch like as Corderius hath at an inſtant, for Engliſh give true Latine<hi>:</hi> for proofe hereof I could produce the teſtimony of diverſe Gentlemen, not all of the loweſt rancke, ſome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of tooke a view of the Childes ability accidentally, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at my requeſt; becauſe I foreſaw the cloud of future clamor and diſgrace, wherewith I was like to bee ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled; it was long in riſing, all the forraine and domeſtick windes met in their chappell and conſiſtory to blow it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. In the ſecond place, that a child of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>George Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes</hi> in Damaske ſtreet, did within ſixe weekes after hee had entered upon the Introduction to Grammar, being then under the age of ſeven years, vary the Verbe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly after the forme aforeſaid, I appeale to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of Maſter <hi>Roger Puttocke</hi> Miniſter of Gods word, and Maſter <hi>Badely</hi> himſelfe, who heard the Childe doe it in the preſence of the Reverend Father in God <hi>William</hi> Lord Biſhop of Kilmore. Diverſe other Children, and ſome ſuperannited, and deſpaired of, have attained the ſame ability within my time li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a quarter of a yeare. Whether I report truth, it may eaſily be examined. And I hope it may be beleived that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Scots</hi> child had attained the ability afore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if it appeare that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Badelyes</hi> child who is little more then nine yeares old, have attained (and not he alone, but ſome others) the ſame ability, within leſſe time. I am almoſt affraid to relate it, leſt it ſhould not be belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but ſhould beget more cenſures. Let him therfore that deſireth to be beſt informed; come and ſatiſfie his own eares, or let him bring me a ſubject to work upon, and he ſhall well ſee, that whatſoever I have affirmed, if my head lay at ſtake, ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance mangre the ſpite of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and detraction be performed, and ſhould have beene proved upon any one, whom I undertooke within my time limitted, that is, two yeares for reading, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14228:8"/>
foure for the Latine, and upon acute ones in much leſſe time, might I be admitted to time and tryall: In perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance whereof my cheifeſt care hath been, is, and ever ſhal be, that by facility and encouragement I beget alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and delight in all, but eſpecially in the moſt way ward and obtuſe, that at no time they be daunted with preſſure and auſterity. If I ſhould give anſwer to every cenſure, I ſhould ſwell into a volume. I will therefore omit all but one, and let my life and labours cleer me living, and my papers, when I am dead; and that one is, it will not hold: I believe verily that young children will not go on with the ſame facility, unleſſe memory and judgment were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, which cannot be expected at nine or ten yeares of age: or unleſſe the ſame method might be proſecuted: yet I ſay had M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Scots</hi> child continued in the way but one yeare more, he had beene fullie confirmed. A compariſon may be drawn from a horſe, his owner, and a rider to help me with moderat men, no cavillers. The owner or maſter committeth his horſe (being a naturall trotter) to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rider, or an Artiſt, that can teach him to amble; he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees at a price to have it done; the rider undertaketh, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on, bringeth the horſe, ſo long as himſelfe rideth him, to a good ſtroke, the horſe over-reacheth a good ſpace; the owner obſerveth it, and before the rider have ſetled and confirmed the horſe in his new pace, taketh the horſe out of his hands, whether out of avarice to ſave his money, or curioſity and over-much haſtines, being overjoyed with his horſes pace, it matters not; but he diſmiſſeth his rider, and rideth the horſe himſelf, falſly ſuppoſing that then he can hold the horſe to his pace, aſwell as the rider: After a while the horſe, by reaſon that the maſter hath not the ſame ſlight of hand for his carriage, is brought to a flutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſhuffling pace, and hath loſt all good pace. Can the rider be juſtly blamed? or ſhall he be condemned to be no Artiſt? Such like is our caſe, untill the method be generally knowne. For thoſe, that be ſo overly and proud, of and in their own wits and judgments, who will not believe, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14228:8"/>
there can be ſuch an invention for the improvement of Art, either becauſe it came not, nor yet is come into their notion, or becauſe it tranſcendeth their capacityes, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe former ages had it not, nor will admit that any mans method can hold equivalency with theirs, as if no mans conceit or invention could mount ſo high a pitch as theirs, I refer ſuch men to the ſtudy of <hi>Almanacks,</hi> out of which they may learn to be ſuch good Chronologiſts, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe time to two of the rareſt inventions, which the earth containeth<hi>:</hi> the one is the Art of <hi>Printing,</hi> the other, the terrible Engyne of the <hi>Gun</hi> and <hi>Cannon,</hi> and the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent devouring matter thereto belonging, the <hi>Powder,</hi> which neither the firſt, nor the ſecond age of the world brought forth, nor the head of this, but even the very taile. For it is not two hundred years ſince the invention of the one, and not three ſince the invention of the other. Much might be ſaid touching the ſeverall methods, and the fruits and effects of them, as alſo touching the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and dignity of teachers and ſchoolemaſters, if they bee ſuch, as they ought to be. But leſt in ſaying more of either, I might ſeem to arrogate that to my ſelfe, which will not be given or granted, I will only ſay of theſe, that they ought to be men endued with Art, method, and diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: art, to underſtand what they teach; method and order, to teach it the right way, and to bring it to the capacity of children, with as much facility as may be; diſcretion to deale with children according to their conſtitutions and capacities. As concerning the methods, and the fruits and effects thereof, let the moſt intelligent caviller, give me anſwer to two queſtions. Firſt, what is the way and ground of reading? Is it any other, then to know the true ſound of every letter, how variouſly ſoever tranſpoſed in mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillable or polyſillable, and to divide polyſillables rightly? and that skill being attained, is not the ground and way of reading? What can be done or required more, but dayly practiſe? Secondly, what is the firſt and cheife ground of Grammar? Is it not the true variation of the declinable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14228:9"/>
parts, whereof the Verb is the moſt perplexed? and that skill being attained, is not the cheife ground of gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar attained? can true connexion be made without true variation? What literate man knoweth not, that the Verb in all languages is the <hi>baſis</hi> of all, and that all the other pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts be but dependants on it, for that no full ſentence or <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce can be ſpoken or written without a Verbe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or underſtood. As I have ſaid before, ſo I ſay againe, the true ground of either may be layd upon a competent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject within a quarter of a yeare, and ſometimes within leſſe time: and then what workman may not finiſh the work? I herefore I conclude thus, <hi>Dimidium facti, qui benè coepit, habet.</hi> And ſo I commit my ſlender invention and practiſe, to the cenſure of the noble, generous and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that they ſeeing the fruit thereof may commend it to poſterity. Then howſoever my paines hath not gotten payment of ſome people, my conſcience ſhall get conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I ſhall confidently ſay at my diſſolution, I have endeavoured to keep a cleere conſcience, I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith henceforth is layde up for mee. &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14228:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
